<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Nat Busa - articles</title><link href="http://natbusa.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://natbusa.github.io/feeds/articles.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://natbusa.github.io/</id><updated>2017-12-18T10:00:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>Simulating Chutes &amp; Ladders in Python</title><link href="http://natbusa.github.io/blog/2017/12/18/simulating-chutes-and-ladders/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-18T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-18T10:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Natalino Busa</name></author><id>tag:natbusa.github.io,2017-12-18:blog/2017/12/18/simulating-chutes-and-ladders/</id><summary type="html">

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://jakevdp.github.io/images/ChutesAndLadders-sim.gif" alt='[img: Chutes and Ladders animated simulation]'&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This weekend I found myself in a particularly drawn-out game of Chutes and Ladders with my four-year-old. If you've not had the pleasure of playing it, Chutes and Ladders (also sometimes known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snakes_and_Ladders"&gt;Snakes and Ladders&lt;/a&gt;) is a classic kids board game wherein players roll a six-sided die to advance forward through 100 squares, using "ladders" to jump ahead, and avoiding "chutes" that send you backward. It's basically a glorified random walk with visual aids to help you build a narrative. Thrilling. But she's having fun practicing counting, learning to win and lose gracefully, and developing the requisite skills to be a &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/904/"&gt;passionate sports fan&lt;/a&gt;, so I play along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the approximately twenty third game of the morning, as we found ourselves in a near endless cycle of climbing ladders and sliding down chutes, never quite reaching that final square to end the game, I started wondering how much longer the game could last: what is the expected length of a game? How heavy are the tails of the game length distribution? How succinctly could I answer those questions in Python? And then, at some point, it &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jakevdp/status/942456865580924928"&gt;clicked&lt;/a&gt;: Chutes and Ladders is memoryless — the effect of a roll depends only on where you are, not where you've been — and so it can be modeled as a Markov process! By the time we (finally) hit square 100, I basically had this blog post written, at least in my head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jakevdp/status/942456865580924928"&gt;tweeted about this&lt;/a&gt;, people pointed me to a &lt;a href="http://www.datagenetics.com/blog/november12011/"&gt;number&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/CamDavidsonPilon/1639d06c448904afaf7b7449910f3b72"&gt;similar&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://math.byu.edu/~jeffh/mathematics/games/chutes/chutes.html"&gt;treatments&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://roycoding.github.io/chutes-ladders-d3/"&gt;Chutes&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://scipython.com/book/chapter-6-numpy/additional-problems/analysing-snakes-and-ladders-as-a-markov-chain/"&gt;Ladders&lt;/a&gt;, so I'm under no illusion that this idea is original.
Think of this as a blog post version of a dad joke: my primary goal is not originality, but self-entertainment, and if anyone else finds it entertaining that's just an added bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="simulation"></category><category term="animation"></category></entry><entry><title>Migrating from Octopress to Pelican</title><link href="http://natbusa.github.io/blog/2013/05/07/migrating-from-octopress-to-pelican/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-07T17:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2013-05-07T17:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Natalino Busa</name></author><id>tag:natbusa.github.io,2013-05-07:blog/2013/05/07/migrating-from-octopress-to-pelican/</id><summary type="html">

&lt;p&gt;After nine months on Octopress, I've decided to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should start by saying that Octopress is a great platform for static
blogging: it's powerful, flexible, well-supported, well-integrated with
GitHub pages, and has tools and plugins to do just about anything you might
imagine.  There's only one problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's written in Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I don't have anything against Ruby per se.  However, it was starting to
seem a bit awkward that a blog called &lt;em&gt;Pythonic Perambulations&lt;/em&gt;
was built with Ruby, especially given the availability of so many
excellent Python-based static site generators
(&lt;a href="http://hyde.github.io/"&gt;Hyde&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://nikola.ralsina.com.ar/"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href="http://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; in particular).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a few things with Octopress were starting to become difficult:
</summary><category term="blogging"></category><category term="octopress"></category><category term="pelican"></category></entry></feed>